So, today's דף Daf in the בבלי Bavli is יב. Yud Bet.
We pick up on יא עמוד ב Yud Aleph Amud Bet in
the middle. And we are continuing with the issue of עיבור השנה.
Ibur Hashana. One point that I meant to make yesterday, David raised
it, actually we saw this more in the ירושלמי Yerushalmi than the
בבלי, Bavli, was it discussed is a חבר Chaver allowed to, like
you know, be sort of present in the בית דין Beit Din
sort of when they do, you know, this, you know, קידוש החודש
Kiddush Hachodesh or עיבור השנה Ibur Hashana etc. Anyway, David made the
point and I meant to make it that when we do the
קידוש, Kiddush, you know, when we when we do the announcement of
ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh in the שול, Shul, we say חברים כל
ישראל ונאמר אמן. Chaverim Kol Yisrael V'nomar Amen. What's this חברים כל
ישראל? Chaverim Kol Yisrael? So it must be, oh, we're all pals,
we're all, you know, friends. It might actually be the technical חבר
Chaver and speaking about that maybe even if, you know, the actual
קידוש השנה Kiddush Hashana קידוש החודש, Kiddush Hachodesh, excuse me, is done
by, you know, you really need like סמוכים Semuchim and whatever, and
you know, only certain, certain, you know, very elevated Rabbis, but the
חברים Chaverim could participate in the proceedings. That was the conclusion of
the ירושלמי Yerushalmi that a חבר Chaver could be מן המנין, Min
Haminyan, you know. So, it was debated. But anyway, so like we're
sort of seeing, you know, the גמרא Gemara sort of uses that
phrase by the way, when it's the רגל. Regel. It says during
the רגל Regel they sort of waived a lot of concerns about
טומאה וטהרה Tuma V'tahara because based on a פסוק Pasuk that says
sort of that, you know, that sort of says that when everybody
comes for the רגל Regel we all unify as one people. So
like everybody's considered like a חבר Chaver for the רגל Regel and
everybody is like trusted in טומאה וטהרה. Tuma V'tahara. It's a משנה
Mishna in חגיגה, Chagigah, you know, very powerful idea. So it could
be that that's פשט Pshat of what we mean when we say
חברים כל ישראל. Chaverim Kol Yisrael. Like this idea that we're all
coming together. Because it's also an interesting thing. How do we do
קידוש החודש? Kiddush Hachodesh? You know, we don't really have a בית
דין, Beit Din, we don't really have, you know, witnesses coming. Yes,
הלל השני Hillel Hasheni set up the calendar, but somehow it's by
acclamation. Like, you know, all of us, you know, recognize that and
that somehow creates the קידוש החודש. Kiddush Hachodesh. So anyway, that's I
just wanted to mention that in terms of the חברים כל ישראל
Chaverim Kol Yisrael sort of line. Anyway, תנו רבנן. Tnu Rabbanan. What?
I was always thinking that, you know, because
more in the colloquial sense that because שנאת חינם Sinat Chinam is
because.
I understand, but now I'm trying to give a very different meaning
to it. Okay, תנו רבנן. Tnu Rabbanan. Bottom of יא עמוד ב
Yud Aleph Amud Bet about 20 lines from the bottom, the two
dots. על שלשה ארצות מעברין את השנה. Al Shlosha Aratzot Meavrin Et
Hashana. For three on on the basis of three different lands you
do, you assess whether it's time to do עיבור השנה. Ibur Hashana.
We just saw this, יהודה ועבר הירדן
והגליל. Yehuda V'ever Hayarden V'hagalil. על שתים Al Shtayim did I do
that? No, I'm sorry, higher than that, excuse me, about ten lines
above that, the earlier two dots. תנו רבנן. Tnu Rabbanan. על שלשה
דברים מעברין את השנה. Al Shlosha Devarim Meavrin Et Hashana. For three
reasons: על האביב ועל פירות האילן ועל התקופה. Al Haaviv, Veal Peirot
Ha'ilan, Veal Hatkufa. So we just did this in בבלי. Bavli. אביב,
Aviv, which is that the grain is not yet ripened. The תקופה,
Tkufa, which is whether it is like, you know, the right season
in terms of is it the fall, is it the winter, is
it the spring, is that coming at the right time. Obviously that
logically would often be linked to אביב. Aviv. And is the fruit
going to be ready
for שבועות Shavuot so people can bring up their ביכורים Bikkurim for
שבועות. Shavuot. Okay, so it says
על שנים מעברין, Al Shnayim Meavrin, for two of these reasons, you
need two of these to do עיבור השנה. Ibur Hashana. ועל אחד
מהם אין מעברין, Veal Achad Mehem Ein Meavrin, but one is not
sufficient. ובזמן Ubizman it does not say what the בבלי Bavli what
the ירושלמי Yerushalmi said, which is בדיעבד B'diavad one would be enough.
It does not make that mention. ובזמן שהאביב אחד מהם הכל שמחים.
Ubizman Sheaviv Echad Mehem Hakol Smechim. When אביב Aviv is one of
them, everybody is very happy. And as רש"י Rashi explains, as I
already told you,
because they want to make sure, if you look at רש"י Rashi
here, let's read רש"י Rashi inside, it's about 15 lines from before
the lines get
wide. ובזמן שהאביב אחד מן השנים שמתעברת השנה עליהן הכל שמחים. Ubizman
Sheaviv Echad Min Hashnayim Shemitaberet Hashana Aleihen Hakol Smechim. שאין חוששים בתחילת
פסח, She'ein Choshim Bit'chilat Pesach, they're not like saying oh my gosh,
you're pushing off פסח. Pesach. לפי שאין תבואה ראויה, Lefi She'ein Tevuah
Reuyah, ואין איסור חדש נערך עליהן. Ve'ein Issur Chadash Ne'erach Aleihen. If
the reality is that the grain isn't ripened, then they don't mind
that we're going to wait another month. Okay, we're going to wait
another month, but it's not like we're going to have grain we
can't eat, the grain isn't ready. Okay? אבל כשהאביב ראוי לקצור, Aval
Kesheaviv Rauy Likatzor, if אביב Aviv is not one of the factors,
so if אביב Aviv is not one of the factors, it means
the grain is
ripened. ואף על פי כן השנה מתעברת על הפירות והתקופה עצבים, Ve'af
Al Pi Ken Hashana Mitaberet Al Hapeirot Veat'kufa Atzeivim, then everybody's upset.
שזמן איסור חדש נערך עליהן, Shezman Issur Chadash Ne'erach Aleihen, because it
means we're going to have ripe grain and we're not going to
have the עומר Omer brought, the עומר Omer being pushed off a
month for the other two reasons. So if it's being done to
coordinate with the ripening of the grain, then we're happy. But if
it's off in terms of the ripening of the grain and it's
the other reasons, we're not happy. Okay? So that's what he says.
רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon Ben Gamliel back to the גמרא.
Gemara. רבן שמעון בן גמליאל אומר על התקופה. Rabban Shimon Ben Gamliel
Omer Al Hatkufa. Even about the תקופה. Tkufa. איבעיא להו. Iba'yu Lehu.
על התקופה שמחים? Al Hatkufa Smechim? Is the תקופה Tkufa reason for
them to be happy? You know, או על התקופה מעברין, O Al
Hatkufa Meavrin, or does he think that the תקופה Tkufa is a
sufficient reason even without the other two? And the גמרא Gemara says
תיקו, Teyku, we don't know. It doesn't explain what the reason would
be that they would be so happy because of the תקופה. Tkufa.
So let's look at רש"י. Rashi. על התקופה שמחים. Al Hatkufa Smechim.
about five lines before it gets wide. היא התקופה נופלת כתיקונה בתחילת
תשרי והם מעברין השנה בשביל דברים אחרים. Hi hatkufa nofeles ketikunah bis-chilas
Tishrei v'heim ma'avrin hashana bishvil dvarim acheirim. If the תקופה tkufa is
okay and not one of the factors. So the seasons are in
the right time and they're pushing it off because of the other
factors, okay, ודוחק את החג בתוך ימי הקור חודש נמצאו עולי רגלים
מצטערים בגשמים לפי שהעתים הולכים אחר
תקופת החמה. V'dochek es hachag b'soch yimei hakor chodesh nimtzu olei regalim
mitza'arim bigshamim lefi sheha'itim holchim achar tkufas hachama. He says if the
תקופה tkufa is one of the factors, then the weather is going
to be right. Everybody loves going to Israel for סוכות. Sukkot. It's
beautiful out in סוכות, Sukkot, right? Perfect time of the year to
be in Israel. So if the תקופה tkufa is synced, then everybody's
happy. The seasons are there, it's beautiful, it's the spring, it's the
fall, it's great. But if the תקופה tkufa is not a factor
and it's the other factors, so then it means that it's going
to be too cold or too hot or too whatever for the
חגים chagim and I'm not going to be happy to do עליה
לרגל aliya l'regel at that time. Okay, so that's his explanation. Okay,
back to the גמרא, Gemara, תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. בשלוש ארצות מעברין
את השנה B'shalosh aratzot ma'avrin et hashana now
where you assess these factors in two on the basis of three
different
regions. יהודה Yehuda ועבר הירדן v'Ever HaYarden והגליל. v'haGalil. על שתיים הן
מעברין Al shtayim hen ma'avrin as if it's true in two of
the regions you do עיבור שנה ibbur shana ועל אחת מהן אין
מעברין v'al achas meihen ein ma'avrin but not if it's only in
one of the regions.
ובזמן שיהודה Uv'zman sheYehuda אחת מהן achas meihen if יהודה Yehuda is
one of them הכל שמחים hakol s'meichim why? שאין עומר בא אלא
מיהודה. She'ein Omer ba ela miYehuda. Now רש"י Rashi says it doesn't
mean literally שאין עומר בא אלא מיהודה she'ein Omer ba ela miYehuda
but you're only supposed to bring it from יהודה, Yehuda, you could
bring it from others. So if things are synchronized with יהודה Yehuda
and it allows us to bring the עומר Omer from יהודה, Yehuda,
we're very happy. Okay, תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. אין מעברין את השנה
אלא ביהודה. Ein ma'avrin es hashana ela b'Yehuda. Now we get to
the question of where you do it, right? We saw in the
ירושלמי Yerushalmi they did it in יהודה Yehuda and then they moved
it from יהודה Yehuda or at least they moved it from לוד.
Lod. Okay but anyway this is the thing, point, you do the
act in יהודה Yehuda ואם עיברוה בגליל מעוברת. v'im ibruah baGalil me'uberet.
But if they did it in the גליל, Galil, it works. העיד
חנניה איש אונו He'id Chananya Ish Ono אם עיברוה בגליל
אינה מעוברת. im ibruah baGalil einah me'uberet. He said he testified that
it didn't work. He probably said one year they did it in
the גליל Galil and it was voided or something, seems like how
else you testify about something like that. It doesn't say it's his
opinion, he's bearing testimony. Okay. He had a tradition. What? Yeah, but
maybe, maybe. What?
Idiom
word?
Yes, it's true, it might, but then it's normally משום mishum like
you say who the tradition is in the name of, it's interesting,
maybe.
Okay, אמר רבי יהודה בריה דרבי שמעון בן פזי Amar Rabbi Yehuda
brei d'Rabbi Shimon ben Pazi מאי טעמא דחנניה איש אונו mai ta'ama
d'Chananya Ish Ono why does he say, it's interesting, I would have
asked the other question. What's the reason to say it's supposed to
be in יהודה. Yehuda. But he says what's the reason to say
that it does work,
I'm sorry, no, that it doesn't work. So he is saying, I'm
sorry, right, what's the reason that he says that the importance of
יהודה, Yehuda, excuse me, is even בדיעבד bedieved and בדיעבד bedieved it
wouldn't work? אמר קרא לשכנו תדרשו ובאת שמה Amar kra l'shichno sidreshu
uvas shamah
the centrality of ירושלים Yerushalayim the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. כל דרישה
שאתה דורש לא יהא אלא בשכנו של מקום. Kol drisha she'atah doresh
lo yehei ela b'shichno shel makom.
Wherever you are seeking out it has to be in the neighborhood
of God, so it has to be in יהודה. Yehuda. But I
don't get how the עיבור שנה ibbur shana is identified with the
concept of being דורש, doresh, right? What does it mean? Because it
required this whole deliberation about whether, you know, what the seasons were,
but it's still דורש doresh more like, you know, religious seeking. I'm
sorry, so it's... Is it why?
Because otherwise you can say they can't be a סנהדרין Sanhedrin of
twenty-three outside of יהודה. Yehuda.
I know, but like I don't understand how דורש doresh is being
linked to the concept of עיבור שנה. ibbur shana. Yes.
ארץ אשר ה' אלהיך דרש אתה. Eretz asher Hashem Elohecha doresh osah.
Oh, you mean so it's being דורש doresh the land and the
well-being... oh that's nice, I like that, the connection that God is
דורש doresh the land in terms of מראשית השנה ועד אחרית שנה.
mereishis hashana v'ad acharis shana. That's actually beautiful. It's like you're looking
at the year and you're assessing what the year... oh thank you,
יישר כוח. shkoach. Okay, that's a good פשט. pshat. Now we're talking.
Okay, so all right. תנו רבנן Tanu Rabbanan so our Rabbis taught.
Now I want to pause for a moment because I need to
say something about not just the centrality of יהודה Yehuda but the
centrality of ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. Okay, and if you take a
look for a moment and look at תוספות, Tosafos, אין מעברין השנה
אלא ביהודה. Ein ma'avrin hashana ela b'Yehuda.
So he says והדר רבי עקיבא עיבר שנה בנהרדעא. v'hadar Rabbi Akiva
iver shana b'Nehardea. That was not just not in יהודה, Yehuda, that
was in בבל. Bavel. בריש פרק האשה שלום B'reish perek HaIsha Shalom
ונהרדעא מחוצה לארץ v'Nehardea michutz la'aretz שנה רבי עקיבא שלא הניח כמותו
בארץ ישראל. Shana Rabbi Akiva shelo hiniach kamoso b'Eretz Yisrael. No,
because there there was no authority equal to him in Israel. כמדאמרן
בסוף ברכות. K'd'amran b'sof Berachos. Okay, and
then somehow if like if the real primary Rabbinic authority is situated
outside of Israel, you don't have to do it in Israel, which
is an interesting idea. And then at the end, I think if
you look like five lines on the bottom of תוספות, Tosafos, he
says ובירושלמי אמרינן בהדיא uv'Yerushalmi amrinan b'hedya I'm sorry, so we haven't
seen this ירושלמי, Yerushalmi, דכשאין יכולים לעברה בארץ ישראל מעברין אותה בחוצה
לארץ, d'cheshe'ein yecholim l'avrah b'Eretz Yisrael ma'avrin osah b'chutz la'aretz, which is
not the same as there are not the same great people in,
you know, in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael as in חוץ לארץ. chutz
la'aretz. It's like it's not somehow possible politically, it's not possible to
do it, then ירמיה Yirmiyah יחזקאל. Yechezkel. ברוך בן נריה עיברו בחוצה
לארץ. Baruch ben Neriah ivru b'Chutza la'Aretz. Okay, והדר מעשה עובדא דחנניה.
vehadar maise uvda d'Chananya.
Okay, so now why is this all so important? Because as I
said, who gets to set the calendar is the basic definition of
where religious authority lies. Because you are defining the entire way in
which the unified way in which people celebrate the חגים. chagim. So
in the period of the גאונים, Geonim, you know, the question why
do we go by the בבלי Bavli not the ירושלמי? Yerushalmi? We
should mention this because we're learning the ירושלמי. Yerushalmi. So the, some
people want to say well, the בבלי Bavli was finished a hundred
years later so they assessed everything the ירושלמי Yerushalmi said. Very questionable
if the בבלי Bavli ever actually knew the ירושלמי Yerushalmi at all.
Anyway, the real reason is because the seat of because the תורה,
Torah, the center of תורה Torah had been shifting over the years
all to בבל, Bavel, right? And that was the total center of
gravity. So it was really a de facto question. When people had
halachic questions, who did they turn to? So more and more the
Jewish community was learning in בבל, Bavel, the understanding that the תורה
Torah greats were in בבל, Bavel, the גאוני בבל, Geonei Bavel, and
by de facto everybody was turning to them and the גאוני בבל
Geonei Bavel used the בבלי, Bavli, they didn't use the ירושלמי. Yerushalmi.
But the reality was, people living in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael were
still turning to the גאוני ארץ ישראל, Geonei Eretz Yisrael, right? So
it wasn't like there was one central authority or central text if
you would. So the deciding the what I call the מכה בפטיש,
maka b'patish, the thing that finally tipped the scales and made it
clear where the authority lied, was there was a in the Geonic
period, I forget exactly what year it was, I think eighth century
I want to say but it might have been ninth, what's a
hundred years between friends? Anyway, there was a question, there's a debate
between בבל Bavel and ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael when the ראש חודש
Rosh Chodesh was going to be. I think it was ראש חודש
תשרי Rosh Chodesh Tishrei if I'm remembering, it might not be. Anyway,
so it wasn't עיבור שנה ibur shana but it was similar, right?
And obviously you could not, we could live with debates about are
you allowed to do X, Y, and Z on שבת, Shabbos, right?
But you cannot have בבל Bavel is having one calendar and ארץ
ישראל Eretz Yisrael another. That's going to break the people, right? You
know, that's going to divide the religion. So they one of them
had to decide. So in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael they said oh,
you know, עיבור שנה, קידוש החודש, ibur shana, kiddush hachodesh, it all
happens in ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. And the גאוני בבל Geonei Bavel
said oh, that's only when לא הניח כמותו, lo hiniach kemoso, you
know, but if it's, you know, that's only all things being equal,
but if the greater, you know, sort of תורה Torah authority is
in בבל, Bavel, then that's where you decide these things, not in
ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. So somehow the גאוני בבל Geonei Bavel won
the day in that debate, and once they won the day, that
really made it very clear that was the final decision, not decision,
whatever, that was the final thing that made it absolutely clear that
the authority rested like in בבל Bavel and not in ארץ ישראל.
Eretz Yisrael. You know, and that's how the בבלי Bavli became to
be like the determinant תלמוד Talmud for all of Jewry. That being
said, אשכנז Ashkenaz still, a lot of פסקים psakim of the רמב"ם
Rambam that don't make any sense are because they're based on the
ירושלמי. Yerushalmi.
אשכנזים Ashkenazim still often מנהגי אשכנז, minhagei Ashkenaz, תוספות Tosafos will say
this, are not always the same as the פסקים psakim in the
בבלי Bavli because they're following the מנהגים minhagim of ארץ ישראל Eretz
Yisrael because Ashkenazi Jewry came from ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael and so
on. So it wasn't all black and white. But anyway, but this
issue of is קידוש החודש kiddush hachodesh or עיבור שנה ibur shana
in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael or בבל Bavel is really a question
of where is the seat of religious authority and it was very
significant in terms of like historically. Okay, so now we continue. Yeah.
How would they in בבל Bavel not know the ירושלמי? Yerushalmi? If
they were scholars traveling back and forth.
Yeah, I mean they knew opinions of various scholars, but did they
know it like a text, you know? So, you know, yeah, there
was obviously communication but the question is like did they know, you
know, yeah, did they have like, I mean obviously I'm not even
talking about a physical text, even as an oral text, did they
know it? Yeah.
תוספות Tosafos they had the ירושלמי. Yerushalmi. So are that's one of
their like missions is to reconcile them?
No, they do not do that systematically. What they do is when
they have a practice that's out of sync with the בבלי, Bavli,
they say how do we make sense of this? And sometimes they
have a way of interpreting the בבלי Bavli and sometimes they say
you know what, it actually it follows the ירושלמי Yerushalmi or it
follows the מנהג ארץ ישראל minhag Eretz Yisrael and guess what, it's
not in sync with the בבלי Bavli and that's the way it
is. Sometimes our מנהגים minhagim are not in accordance with the בבלי.
Bavli.
Not a theoretical difference, it was more like...
No, no, no, he does not sort of see it as a
job to sort of work at dealing with the texts of the
ירושלמי. Yerushalmi. His job is to deal with all the texts of
the בבלי Bavli and try to make them consistent. Yeah, not with
the ירושלמי. Yerushalmi. Okay, so now let's go back. תנו רבנן, tanu
rabanan, אין מעברין את השנה אלא ביום, ein ma'avrin es hashana ela
bayom,
you only do it in the daytime, this we haven't seen yet.
ואם עיברוה בלילה, v'im ivruha balaila, if they did it at nighttime,
אינה מעוברת, eina meuberes, it doesn't work. ואין מקדשין את החודש אלא
ביום, v'ein mikadshin es hachodesh ela bayom, and קידוש החודש kiddush hachodesh
is also in the daytime. ואם קידשוהו בלילה, v'im kidshuhu balaila, if
they sanctified it at night, אינו מקודש, eino mekudash, it doesn't work
at night, which is interesting because that's when you see the new
moon, but that's not necessarily when you do the active קידוש החודש.
kiddush hachodesh. אמר רבי אבא, amar Rabbi Abba, מאי קרא, mai kra,
what's the pasuk? תקעו בחודש שופר בכסא ליום חגנו. tik'u bachodesh shofar
bakeseh l'yom chageinu. So blow the shofar in the in the covering
up of the day of our rejoicing. איזו חג eizo chag Which
is also the daytime. ובין מקדשי בלילה אין מקודש, U'vein mikadshei balailah
ein mekudash, it doesn't work at night, which is interesting because that's
when you see the new moon, but that's not necessarily when you
do the act of קידוש החודש. Kiddush HaChodesh. אמר רבי אבא, Amar
Rabbi Abba, מאי קרא, mai kra, what's the פסוק? pasuk? תקעו בחודש
שופר בכסה ליום חגנו. Tiku bachodesh shofar bakeseh l'yom chageinu. So blow
the shofar in the when in the in the covering up of
the day of our rejoicing. איזהו חג שהחודש מתכסה בו? Eizehu chag
shehachodesh mitkasseh bo? What is the only holiday that the moon is
not seen? הוי אומר ראש השנה. Hevei omer Rosh Hashanah. That's ראש
השנה. Rosh Hashanah. Okay, וכתיב כי חוק לישראל הוא, U'chsiv ki chok
l'Yisrael hu, and identifies this as a חוק. chok. So what is
the only holiday that the moon is not seen? הוי אומר ראש
השנה, Hevei omer Rosh Hashanah, that's ראש השנה. Rosh Hashanah. Okay, וכתיב
כי חוק לישראל הוא U'chsiv ki chok l'Yisrael hu and identifies this
as a חוק, chok, so משפט לאלהי יעקב mishpat l'Elohei Yaakov and
משפט, mishpat, judgment. מה משפט ביום, ma mishpat beyom, so the creating
of ראש השנה, Rosh Hashanah, קידוש החודש, Kiddush HaChodesh, which is, you
know, ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah is made through the act of קידוש
החודש, Kiddush HaChodesh, that is like a משפט. mishpat. מה משפט ביום,
ma mishpat beyom, the same way בית דין beis din meets during
the day and not at night, אף קידוש החודש ביום, af Kiddush
HaChodesh beyom, the same is true by קידוש החודש. Kiddush HaChodesh. Okay.
תנו רבנן, tanu rabanan, אין מעברין את השנה, ein me'abrin es hashana,
finally we're on דף י"ב, daf yud beis, אין מעברין את השנה
ein me'abrin es hashana בשני רעבון. bishnei ra'avon.
You don't do it during a period of famine. Why not?
Because you don't want whatever your other factors might be, you do
not want to delay bringing the עומר, omer, because bringing the עומר
omer is just going to make it harder for people to get
food, you know, and they need food earlier.
תניא, tanya, we taught in a ברייתא, braisa, רבי אומר, Rabbi omer,
ואיש בא מבעל שלישה ויבא לאיש האלוהים לחם ביכורים עשרים לחם שעורים.
v'ish ba miba'al shalisha vayavei l'ish ha'elohim lechem bikurim esrim lechem se'orim.
So this is one of those miracles, you know, that אלישע Elisha
did, and they basically brought this bread and then it was fed
all these people. Anyway, so this person came and it was clear
that it was a time of famine and from this bread they
it was a miracle they fed all these people. So he brought
to the man of God, to אלישע, Elisha, the ripened bread of
twenty loaves. עשרים לחם שעורים. esrim lechem se'orim. Okay, ואין לך קלה
בכל ארץ ישראל לבשל פירותיה יותר מבעל שלישה. v'ein l'cha kala bechol
eretz yisrael l'vashel peiroseha yoser miba'al shalisha.
This region was the place that was the fastest where the grain
would become ripened in all of Israel. ואף על פי כן לא
ביכרה אלא מין אחד, v'af al pi chein lo bikra ela min
echad, and only the שעורים, se'orim, only the barley was ripe. The
wheat wasn't ripe yet. שמא תאמר לפני העומר, shema tomar lifnei ha'omer,
now let's let's say you say, oh, well, that was because it
was early in the year, it was before the עומר. omer. תלמוד
לומר תן לעם ויאכלו. talmud lomar ten l'am veyocheilu. אלישע Elisha said,
give to the people, let them eat. So אחר העומר היה, achar
ha'omer haya, it was after the עומר. omer. So here it was,
it was after the עומר, omer, it was the place where the
grain ripens the fastest, and nevertheless, only the barley was ripe and
the wheat had not begun ripening. היה אומר מעתה ראויה הייתה זו
שנה שתתעבר. haya omer me'ata re'uya haysa zo shana shetis'aber.
So really, that should have been an עיבור שנה. ibur shana. He
should have postponed the עומר, omer, you know, postponed פסח, Pesach, postponed
the עומר omer because of אביב, aviv, so that more of the
grain would be ripe. Okay, ומפני מה לא עיברה, u'mipnei mah lo
ibra, אלישע, Elisha, why did אלישע Elisha not do an עיבור שנה?
ibur shana? ששנת בצורת הייתה, sheshnas batzores haysa, because it was a
famine was clear from the narrative. והיו הכל רצין לבית הגרנות, v'hayu
hakol ratzin l'veis hagranos, and everybody's running to the, you know, to
the threshing floors, everybody needed the grain, so you had to, so
even though it was going to be ripened, you know, even though
the עומר omer would be brought and things were only just beginning
to ripen, so say, no, let's wait until it's more אביב, aviv,
till, you know, till the wheat starts ripening, other things, you know,
other grain in other areas starts ripening. But no, let's not make
anybody delay being able to eat the new grain. So even though
it's not going to be the big the real full אביב, aviv,
we should not be delaying the coming of פסח. Pesach. Okay, תנו
רבנן, tanu rabanan, which by the way is interesting because it also
makes it sound that part of the אביב aviv is that you
want it to be a period not only where the barley ripens,
but where the wheat ripens. Right? Normally, you know, you assume that
like פסח Pesach is the time the barley is ripe and the
wheat becomes ripe, you know, you know, a month after whatever, like
doing that's always what I assumed, what do I know, I'm not
a farmer, I know my agriculture from רש"י, Rashi, you know. So
anyway, but somebody will tell me otherwise, but anyway, you know, because
on פסח, Pesach, you know, you bring the עומר omer from the
from the barley, and on שבועות Shavuos you bring the שתי הלחם
shtei halechem from the from the wheat. And I always assumed that,
you know, פסח Pesach time the barley is ripe and the wheat
starts ripening after פסח. Pesach. But here it sounds, and רש"י Rashi
says says it explicitly, that אביב, aviv, which is the פסח Pesach
time, you want it to be the time that the wheat has
started to ripen as well. So maybe it means at least some
places the wheat is ripened, maybe it's not fully ripened yet.
Yes, I think at the time, at that time, wheat was ripening
twice a year. Uh-huh. Not the same type, but the same grain.
Ah,
so it ripened both like both in פסח Pesach and then a
second type of wheat? Yes. Just a few months later in the,
oh, interesting. So very good, good to know. Okay. Okay, תנו רבנן,
tanu rabanan, אין מעברין את השנה לפני ראש השנה. ein me'abrin es
hashana lifnei Rosh Hashanah.
You can't do it, you know, six months in advance, before ראש
השנה. Rosh Hashanah. It has to be like in the second half
of the year. Obviously, ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah here is not twelve
months in advance, right? Because you do עיבור שנה, ibur shana, it's
אדר, Adar, it's before ניסן. Nissan. So your ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah
is half is in mid-year. Okay, don't let that confuse you. You
can't do it before, you know, before ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah six
months in advance. ואם עיברוה אינה מעוברת. v'im ibruha eina me'uberes. And
even if you did it, it didn't work. אבל מפני הדוחק, aval
mipnei hadochak,
but if it's a time of pressure, the pressure would be, רש"י
Rashi says it might be political pressure, that, you know, that the
because of the Roman government or other things. Again, this was an
exercise of religious power. So sometimes they were constrained about when and
where they could do it. So if there are these types of
constraints, מעברין אותה אחר ראש השנה מיד. ma'avrin osa achar Rosh Hashanah
miyad. We'd like it to be closer to the time of, because
because then you're more able to have the relevant
data. properly if you're supposed to do it or not. And also
people will like take note of it more when it's closer to
the relevant time. But nevertheless, if there's pressure, you're allowed to do
it right after ראש השנה. Rosh Hashanah. ואף על פי כן אין
מעברין אלא אדר
ve-af al pi chen
ein me-abrin ela adar
but regardless, even if you're doing it six, you know, way at
ראש השנה, Rosh Hashanah, the only month you're allowed to add is
אדר. Adar. Now why is this? So take a look at תוספות,
Tosafot, the גמרא Gemara never says why this is, but take a
look now I we I would always assume it's because it's based
on חודש האביב chodesh ha-aviv right and פסח Pesach has to be
חודש האביב chodesh ha-aviv so therefore it's about it's about, you know,
getting פסח Pesach right so therefore the month you fix has to
be the month before פסח. Pesach. תוספות Tosafot gives a different reason.
Look at תוספות: Tosafot: אין מעברין אלא אדר וכל שאר חודשים אין
מעברין. ein me-abrin ela adar ve-chol she-ar chodashim ein me-abrin. Why? דכתיב
dechativ בחודש שנים עשר הוא חודש אדר. be-chodesh shenayim asar hu chodesh
adar. ואם מעברין אחד משאר החודשים לא היה אדר שנים עשר ve-im
me-abrin echad mi-she-ar ha-chodashim lo haya adar shenayim asar
because the פסוק pasuk in Esther says אדר Adar is the 12th
month. So therefore the only way, right, and it says ניסן, Nisan,
you know, is, you know, you know, is the first month, and
תשרי Tishrei is the seventh month, so the only way you're not
going to get those numberings off is if you add a 13th
month. If you add any other month you're going to get the
numbers off. So it's a fascinating reason. Anyway, but it's it's interesting
that the גמרא Gemara never gives the reason. Okay, so back to
the גמרא. Gemara. Okay.
איני eini is this really true? והא שלחו ליה לרבא ve-ha shalchu
leh le-Rava they sent to רבא Rava זוג בא מרקבת zug ba
mi-rakat so here's going to be a little like call it a
little cryptic message. Okay. A pair has come from רקבת, Rakat, which
רש"י Rashi says is Tiberia, a pair of תלמידי חכמים talmidei chachamim
ותפסו נשר ve-tafso nesher and the eagle has seized them. Who do
you think the eagle is? Rome. Okay, you know, they had the
eagle on their banner. ובידם דברים הנעשים בלוז u-vi-yadam devarim ha-na'asim be-luz
and they were holding on to things that were done in לוז,
Luz, which is and the גמרא Gemara says inserts ומאי ניהו תכלת.
u-mai nihu techelet. תכלת techelet was made in לוז, Luz, okay.
בזכות הרחמים bi-zechut ha-rachamim and maybe I don't know, somehow they were
violating some edict or something by maybe they weren't paying taxes on
the תכלת, techelet, you know, תכלת techelet was a very controlled substance
because it was like the royal blue. So could be that the
Roman government, you know, had some interest in that. So they got
in
trouble. Okay. ובזכות הרחמים ובזכותם יצאו בשלום. u-vi-zechut ha-rachamim u-vi-zechutam yatz'u be-shalom.
Somehow they managed to come out unharmed. ועמוסי ירכי נחשון ve-amusei yarchei
nachshon and those who were from the, you know, the descendants of
the loins of נחשון, Nachshon, meaning, you know, נחשון בן עמינדב, Nachshon
ben Aminadav, so they were basically like, you know, descendants of יהודה
Yehuda and so on, of דוד המלך, David HaMelech, so which is
like the נשיא's Nasi household, descendants of the נשיא, Nasi, בקשו לקבוע
נציב bikshu likvo'a natziv they wanted to establish, you know, the a
month, we're going to see in a minute that the word נציב
natziv means like a month, they wanted to add an extra month
to the year, also the word, you know, do an עיבור שנה
ibur shanah ולא הניחן אדומי הלז ve-lo hinichan adomi ha-laz and this
Edomite did not allow them, the Edomite being Rome. It's a very
cute little cryptic little passage. Okay, so the Roman government prevented them
from doing it. אבל בעלי אסופות aval ba'alei asupot those who gather
things, which is often referred to as like the, you know, תורה
Torah scholars, נאספו ne'esfu they gathered, they so the תלמידי חכמים talmidei
chachamim gathered וקבעו לו נציב אחד בירח ve-kav'u lo natziv echad be-yerach
and they established an extra month בירח שמת בו אהרן הכהן be-yerach
she-met bo aharon ha-kohen and when did they do this? They did
this in the month that אהרן Aaron died. Anybody knows the month
that אהרן Aaron died?
אב. Av. Okay, this month. Okay. So חשובי מחשבי גלויי לא מגלו
chashuvei machshvei galuyei lo me-galu so anyway, so that's our question. So
it's clear that was very clear. So anyway, it says they did
עיבור שנה ibur shanah in אב. Av. How could they do עיבור
שנה ibur shanah in אב, Av, right? That's before ראש השנה. Rosh
Hashanah. So the גמרא Gemara says: חשובי מחשבי גלויי לא מגלו. chashuvei
machshvei galuyei lo me-galu. No, no, no.
They did the like
calculations, you know, and they determined we were going to have to
do an עיבור שנה ibur shanah and they made that decision, but
they didn't announce it. Or if you want to say they didn't
officially do the act to create the עיבור שנה, ibur shanah, they
just sort of made the decision to do it. They did the
calculations. Okay, now the גמרא's Gemara going to try to unpack this
statement a little bit. מאי משמע דהאי נציב לישנא דירחא הוא mai
mashma de-hai natziv lishna de-yarcha hu
how do you know this נציב natziv this extra נציב natziv means
an extra month? Where does the word נציב natziv mean a month?
דכתיב dechativ ולשלמה שנים עשר נציבים. u-li-shlomo shenayim asar netzivim.
שלמה Shlomo appointed 12 officers על כל ישראל al kol yisrael וכלכלו
את המלך ve-chalkelu et ha-melech
and these officers had the responsibility of providing, you know, of
sustenance for the king, of basically like raising the taxes, or whatever
it was, ואת ביתו ve-et beito חודש בשנה chodesh ba-shanah each one
took a different month of the year. So the idea of an
officer over a month, you know, assigned per month, that was why
in this sort of coded message, obviously coded presumably to not so
that the Romans wouldn't figure out what they were talking about, right?
Anyway, so that's why they used. use the word נציב natziv to
refer to a month. So the גמרא Gemara says wait a minute,
דכתיב dechetiv ונציב אחד אשר בארץ, unatziv echad asher ba'aretz, there was
only one נציב natziv over the land. So Rabbi Yehuda v'Rav Nachman,
חד אמר chad amar ממונה על כולם. memuna al kulam. Okay, he
was the one over the twelve. But still each one of you
know the normal נציב natziv was only over one month. וחד אמר
כנגד חודש עיבור. vechad amar keneged chodesh ibur. No,
there was an extra נציב natziv just for the second אדר. Adar.
Okay, then that was his job when they would have a second
אדר. Adar. תנו רבנן, Tanu rabanan, back to this question about the
parameters of עיבור שנה. ibur shanah. אין מעברין את השנה לא משנה
לחברתה, ein me'avrin et hashanah lo mishanah lachaverta, not from one year
to the next. Now what does this mean? There's a debate of
רש"י Rashi and תוספות. Tosafot. רש"י Rashi says it means I'm not
going to say let's make this year an עיבור שנה ibur shanah
so next year the seasons will fall out properly. You can only
make it an עיבור שנה ibur shanah if it addresses the issues
of this year. תוספות Tosafot says it means you can't do it
in advance. Like you can't sort of say
right now we're in 5777 and we're going to decide that 5778
is going to be an עיבור שנה. ibur shanah. Now that should
be obvious because we said you can't even do it before ראש
השנה. Rosh Hashanah. So תוספות Tosafot says well maybe it means you
can't even make the calculation you know more than a year in
advance. You can't do the announcement until after ראש השנה, Rosh Hashanah,
but you can't even make the calculation right because you're twenty factors
you don't know, so you can't even make the calculation more than
a year in advance. That's the way תוספות Tosafot reads it. ולא
שלוש שנים זו אחר זו, v'lo shalosh shanim zo achar zo, and
you can't do it three years in a row. That would just
set everything out of whack. אמר רבי שמעון מעשה ברבי עקיבא, Amar
Rabbi Shimon ma'aseh b'Rabbi Akiva, wait a minute there was a story
with רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva שהיה חבוש בבית האסורים, shehayah chavush b'veit
ha'asurim, he was being held in the Roman jail, right this was
obviously leading up to his martyrdom, ועיבר שלוש שנים זו אחר זו,
ve'ibar shalosh shanim zo achar zo, and they basically did three years
in a row because they went, they sent a little you know
contingent there to consult with רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. He was a
huge תלמיד חכם, talmid chacham, he understood this stuff, and they planned
out the calendar three years in a row. So the גמרא Gemara
says so how do you make sense of that? So the גמרא
Gemara says אמרו לו משם ראיה, amru lo misham rayah, you want
to bring a proof from there? בית דין ישבו וקבעו אחת אחת
בזמנה. Beit din yashvu vekavu achat achat bizmanah. They may have figured
out
in advance that they three years that were going to be עיבור
שנה, ibur shanah, but each one was only done in its right
time. Now the question is wait a minute, who cares if each
one was done in its right time if the reality was that
you had three leap years all lined up? So there's a question
how to read the answer. One way to read the answer is
no no no, they figured out when the next three leap years
were going to be, but the next three leap years weren't all
weren't all you know one right after the other. The other answer
is no maybe actually they did do three leap years in a
row and when it says you don't do three in a row
what it means is that you don't sort of like you know
determine ahead of time that there're going to be three. But it
doesn't mean that there can't actually be three in a row. So
the answer was okay so they thought it out but then they
actually when it came to doing it you know they reassessed each
one in the right time. So it's not exactly clear like what
is the parameters, what are the what are the you know what
are the guidelines and how this solved the problem. But anyway an
easy way to read this is is that you are you know
that which is not necessarily the most פשט pshat reading of the
words but is that you know they determined ahead of time when
the next three would be but they weren't three in a row.
They were the three when they actually occurred whenever that was going
to be. Okay anyway now the גמרא Gemara continues
תנו רבנן, Tanu rabanan, אין מעברין את השנה לא בשביעית ולא במוצאי
שביעית. ein me'avrin et hashanah lo bishvi'it velo b'motza'ei shvi'it. You don't
do it on שמיטה Shmita because obviously then you're just extending the
time that you can't plant and you don't do it the year
after שמיטה Shmita because then you're extending the time that
you know because everybody is waiting the year after שמיטה Shmita for
the עומר Omer to be brought as soon as possible so you
could start eating the new wheat from the stuff you planted as
soon as possible. So if you do an עיבור שנה ibur shanah
the year after שמיטה Shmita you're delaying the eating of the new
wheat for another
month. Okay, אימתי רגילין לעבר, Eimatai regilin l'aber, when would they often
do it? ערב שביעית. Erev shvi'it. That's a good time to have
an extra month, right give people an extra month of planting and
harvesting before שמיטה Shmita comes
about. שבבית רבן גמליאל היו מעברין במוצאי שביעית. Shebeiv Raban Gamliel hayu
me'avrin b'motza'ei shvi'it. Now in בית רבן גמליאל Beit Raban Gamliel they
would do it מוצאי שביעית. motza'ei shvi'it. How did they do it?
It's going to cause everybody to have to wait a month to
eat the new grain? So the גמרא Gemara says ובפלוגתא דהני תנאי,
uv'plugta d'hani tanna'ei, it's that's based on the following debate of תנאי.
tanna'ei. דתניא, Detanya, we learn in a ברייתא, braita, אין מביאין ירק
מחוצה לארץ. ein mevi'in yerak michutzah la'aretz. You don't bring vegetables, you
don't import vegetables from outside of Israel. ורבותינו התירו, v'raboteinu hitiru, and
our rabbis allowed it. Whoever the רבותינו raboteinu is. מאי בינייהו, Mai
beinaihu, what this debate about? אמר רבי ירמיה חוששין לגושין איכא בינייהו.
Amar Rabbi Yirmiyah chosheshin l'gushin ikka beinaihu. Are you concerned about the
dirt that comes with the vegetables? Because the dirt of חוצה לארץ
chutza la'aretz is טמא tamei if you touch it. So do we
want to import vegetables if it's going to mean bringing in the
dirt and that might lead to טומאה tumah problems? So רבן גמליאל'ס
Raban Gamliel's household says that you do bring in the vegetables. If
you do bring in the vegetables, we can have an עיבור שנה
ibur shanah right after שמיטה. Shmita. Oh what are people going to
eat? Well we'll just import import more food from חוץ לארץ. Chutz
L'aretz. Now it's interesting because you would think the house of the
נשיא, nasi, forget the halakhic considerations, it's like whatever, that's the whole
free trade issue. But you want to be thinking encouraging ארץ ישראל
Eretz Yisrael to be self-sufficient agriculturally and not make a decision that
sort of says it'll be okay because we can just import the
fruit, import the food that we need. But that was actually the
debate. Okay. So תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan, אין מעברין את השנה מפני
הטומאה. ein m'abrin et hashana mipnei hatumah. Let's say there's a concern
that people are טמא tamei and therefore if we add a month
we'll be able to get more people to bring the קרבן פסח
korban Pesach because people will have a chance to become טהור. tahor.
רבי יהודה אומר מעבירין. Rabbi Yehuda omer m'abrin. No,
the first answer is that's not a good enough reason, and רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says it is a good enough reason. אמר רבי
יהודה מעשה בחזקיה מלך יהודה שעיבר את השנה מפני הטומאה. Amar Rabbi
Yehuda ma'aseh b'Chizkiyah Melech Yehuda she'eibur et hashana mipnei hatumah. חזקיה Chizkiyah
did it, okay? And this was because of טומאה. tumah. וביקש רחמים
על עצמו u'vikeish rachamim al atzmo and even and then he asked
for forgiveness because he shouldn't have done it. Now that's bizarre because
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda first says you're allowed to do it for
טומאה tumah and then it says חזקיה Chizkiyah did it, brings support,
and then it says and then חזקיה Chizkiyah had to ask for
forgiveness. So the גמרא's Gemara going to try to figure out what
רבי יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda actually saying. But anyway דכתיב d'chtiv כי מרבית
העם רבת מאפרים ומנשה יששכר וזבולן לא הטהרו, ki marbit ha'am rabat
me'Ephraim u'Menashe Yissachar u'Zevulun lo hitaharu, that this was in the time
of חזקיה Chizkiyah they brought a קרבן פסח, korban Pesach, right? And
they had this whole religious revival, and it says but the vast
numbers of the people were not pure. Okay, and then the next
פסוק pasuk says כי אכלו את הפסח בלא ככתוב. ki achlu et
haPesach b'lo kakatuv. They ate the קרבן פסח korban Pesach against what
was written. Now פשט pshat of the פסוקים psukim means they ate
the קרבן פסח בטומאה. korban Pesach b'tumah. Okay, but that's not the
way the גמרא's Gemara reading it. First of all, if the majority
of people were טמא, tamei, then you'd be allowed to eat the
קרבן פסח בטומאה. korban Pesach b'tumah. טומאה הותרה בציבור. tumah hutra b'tzibbur.
But number two is for some reason the גמרא's Gemara choosing to
read this not that they actually violated that, the violation was that
he saw that people were טמא, tamei, he decided to solve the
problem by adding an extra month. He wasn't supposed to do this
and that was the violation. The violation was that they celebrated פסח
Pesach at what should not have been the right time because they
did the עיבור שנה eibur shana wrong. I bet you never thought
that that was what was going on in those פסוקים, psukim, but
okay, that's the way the גמרא's Gemara understanding it. כי התפלל חזקיה
עליהם, ki hitpalel Chizkiyah aleihem, he prayed for them לאמר השם הטוב
יכפר בעד. leimor Hashem hatov yichaper b'ad. So there he's praying for
forgiveness. So we're reading the forgiveness is that he shouldn't have added
the month and done an עיבור שנה. eibur shana. רבי שמעון אומר
אם מפני הטומאה עיברוה מעוברת. Rabbi Shimon omer im mipnei hatumah ibrunah
m'uberet. No, that wouldn't have been a problem. You're allowed to do
עיבור שנה eibur shana because of טומאה. tumah. אלא מה ביקש רחמים
על עצמו? ella mah bikeish rachamim al atzmo? What was he praying
for forgiveness for? שאין מעברין אלא אדר she'ein m'abrin ella Adar that
you're only allowed to add אדר Adar והוא עיבר ניסן בניסן. v'hu
ibur Nissan b'Nissan. He made his decision after it was already ראש
חודש ניסן. Rosh Chodesh Nissan. And he said, "Oh, let's add another
ניסן Nissan and we'll bring פסח Pesach on the second ניסן, Nissan,
not on the first ניסן." Nissan. So that was like a big
mistake and then everybody ate the קרבן פסח korban Pesach at the
wrong time. Okay. רבי שמעון בן יהודה אומר משום רבי שמעון מפני
שהשיא את ישראל לעשות פסח שני. Rabbi Shimon ben Yehuda omer mishum
Rabbi Shimon mipnei shehisi et Yisrael la'asot Pesach sheini. No, his sin
was that he took all these טמא tamei people and he told
them, "All you guys go to bring a פסח שני." Pesach sheini.
And he shouldn't have said that, because if everybody was טמא, tamei,
טומאה הותרה בציבור tumah hutra b'tzibbur and they could have eaten a
פסח ראשון. Pesach rishon. So we have all these fascinating explanations rather
than just פשט pshat of the פסוקים... psukim... it's funny like what
is motivating חז"ל Chazal to say this? Sometimes you figure they want
to protect like a biblical figure and say he didn't really sin.
But they're saying he did sin, right? So why not just say
that the sin was that he had people eat the קרבן פסח
korban Pesach even though they were טמא? tamei? So I guess that's
not as interesting as these other explanations, but it's giving all these
reasons. Okay. So now the גמרא's Gemara going to unpack it. So
let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. אמר מר רבי יהודה
אומר מעבירין אלמא סבירא ליה לרבי יהודה טומאה דחויה היא בציבור. Amar
mar Rabbi Yehuda omer m'abrin alma sevira leh l'Rabbi Yehuda tumah dchuya
hi b'tzibbur. So what is this debate is, is טומאה tumah a
good enough reason to add a month? So the גמרא Gemara ties
it into this very central question. Is טומאה הותרה בציבור tumah hutra
b'tzibbur or דחויה בציבור? dchuya b'tzibbur? Which means is the תורה Torah
sort of like saying the laws of טומאה tumah don't apply when
there's all these הלכות halachot that you're not allowed to eat if
you're טמא tamei whatever, that's only when it's about individuals. When it's
a ציבור, tzibbur, those laws were never set in such a case.
That's הותרא. hutra. Or do we say, no, no, no, the restrictions
still are present, but it's overridden by more weighty considerations. The classic
place people know this issue is by שבת. Shabbat. Like do you
say that the תורה Torah never told us to keep שבת Shabbat
when a life was at stake? It only told us keep שבת
Shabbat under normal circumstances. The מצוה mitzvah of שבת Shabbat doesn't apply
when a life is at stake. Or do you say no, no,
no, of course the מצוה mitzvah of שבת Shabbat applies, you're still
somehow violating שבת, Shabbat, but there are more important things than שבת.
Shabbat. Life is more important than שבת. Shabbat. So that
legitimates שבת Shabbat to be broken. So that's the conceptual question of
הותרא hutra versus דחויה. dchuya. So the גמרא Gemara says here's a
perfect example. If it's דחויה, dchuya, if it's being overridden but being
violated, then that means that if there's a way
to prevent the conflict, then you should try to prevent it, right?
So therefore... Or if you can add an extra month and get
people to not be טמא, tamei, that's better than having them טמא
tamei and eating the קרבן פסח Korban Pesach even if it's going
to be a ציבור Tzibur that's טמא tamei and it's going to
be allowed, why should we go for an override when we could
avoid the problem all together? So if you say טומאה דחויה בציבור,
Tuma Dechuya B'Tzibur, then it's a good reason to do עיבור שנה.
Ibur Shana. If טומאה הותרה בציבור, Tuma Hutra B'Tzibur, there's no violation
at all, then it's not a good reason to do עיבור שנה.
Ibur Shana. So that's how the גמרא Gemara conceptualizes the debate. So
let's read this. אמא איסא דרבי יהודה Ama Isa de Rebbe Yehuda
for רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda says it's a reason to do עיבור
שנה, Ibur Shana, טומאה דחויה בציבור. Tuma Dechuya B'Tzibur. It's only overridden
and pushed aside and therefore we should try to avoid the problem.
But one minute, והתניא ve-hatanya we taught in a ברייתא, Braita, ציץ
Tzitz the headplate on the כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, בין שישנו על
מצחו בין שאינו על מצחו, bein sheyeshno al mitzcho bein she-eino al
mitzcho, whether he's wearing it on his forehead or not מרצה. meratze.
The purpose of the ציץ Tzitz the תורה Torah says is that
it atones for קרבנות korbanot that are brought בטומאה. be-tuma. So one
opinion is that only works to make the קרבנות korbanot acceptable post
facto if the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol was wearing it when the
קרבן korban was brought. דברי רבי שמעון. Divrei Rebbe Shimon. That's what
רבי שמעון Rebbe Shimon says. רבי יהודה אומר, Rebbe Yehuda Omer, עודו
על מצחו מרצה, odo al mitzcho meratze, if he's wearing it, it
makes the קרבן korban acceptable even though it was טמא, tamei, אינו
עודו על מצחו אינו מרצה, eino odo al mitzcho eino meratze, if
it's not on his forehead it does not work. אמר ליה רבי
שמעון, Amar lei Rebbe Shimon, רבי שמעון Rebbe Shimon said to him,
כהן גדול ביום הכיפורים יוכיח. Kohen Gadol b'Yom HaKippurim yochiach. You can't
say that because how about on יום כיפור? Yom Kippur? The כהן
גדול Kohen Gadol is wearing the white garments, he's not wearing the
ציץ Tzitz and we know שאינו על מצחו, she-eino al mitzcho, it's
not on his forehead and מרצה meratze and we know that if
there's a טומאה tuma problem with a קרבן korban on יום כיפור,
Yom Kippur, the קרבן korban is acceptable. So you see he doesn't
have to be wearing it. אמר לו רבי יהודה, Amar lo Rebbe
Yehuda, רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda said back to him, הנח ליום הכיפורים,
henach l'Yom HaKippurim, don't go talking to me about יום כיפור, Yom
Kippur, שטומאה הותרה בציבור, she-tuma hutra b'tzibur, טומאה tuma is overridden בציבור
b'tzibur and that's why it's okay, it's not okay because of the
ציץ. Tzitz. Okay, and so now that's fine. So that's a debate
about the ציץ. Tzitz. But what's relevant to us is that his
phrase he used was טומאה הותרה בציבור. Tuma Hutra B'Tzibur. He didn't
say טומאה דחויה. Tuma Dechuya. So if רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda actually
says טומאה הותרה בציבור, Tuma Hutra B'Tzibur, then why should we add
an extra month in order to avoid the problem? So the גמרא
Gemara says, okay, ולטעמיך, u-l'tameicha, the גמרא Gemara says one minute, even
put that aside. רבי יהודה's Rebbe Yehuda statement didn't make sense on
its own terms. ולטעמיך u-l'tameicha according it says תיקשי לך היא גופא.
tikshi lach hee gufa. Look at the statement itself. רבי יהודה אומר
מעברין, Rebbe Yehuda Omer Me-abrin, you add a month, and then the
next line said ואמר רבי יהודה מעשה בחזקיה מלך יהודה שעיבש את
השנה מפני הטומאה וביקש רחמים על עצמו. ve-amar Rebbe Yehuda ma'aseh b'Chizkiya
melech Yehuda she-ibash et ha-shana mipnei ha-tuma u-vikesh rachamim al atzmo. That
חזקיה Chizkiya added a month because of טומאה tuma and then he
asked for forgiveness. So that sounds like you're not supposed to add
a month. So which is it? Which is רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda
saying? אלא חסורי מחסרא והכי קתני, Ela chisuri michasra ve-hachi katani, it
has to be this ברייתא's braita missing some words and here's how
you read it. אין מעברין את השנה מפני הטומאה ואם עיברו מעוברת.
Ein me-abrin et ha-shana mipnei ha-tuma ve-im ibru me-uberet. You don't do
it but בדיעבד be-di'avad it works. רבי יהודה אומר אינה מעוברת. Rebbe
Yehuda omer eina me-uberet. We actually change the position. Not that רבי
יהודה Rebbe Yehuda says you do it, we had- we take רבי
יהודה Rebbe Yehuda from saying לכתחילה le-chatchila you're doing it, to saying
that even בדיעבד be-di'avad it doesn't work. He goes from exactly one
extreme to the next the way we've re-read רבי יהודה. Rebbe Yehuda.
But now it fits with what he says about חזקיה. Chizkiya. ואמר
רבי יהודה Ve-amar Rebbe Yehuda etc. So therefore now we've solved the
problem because A, רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda now is saying not you're
allowed to do it but you're not allowed to do it and
doesn't work, and that's why חזקיה Chizkiya had to ask for forgiveness.
And now it is completely consistent with רבי יהודה's Rebbe Yehuda position
that טומאה הותרה בציבור. Tuma Hutra B'Tzibur. If טומאה הותרה בציבור, Tuma
Hutra B'Tzibur, then being טמא tamei is not a legitimate reason. I
want to just pause for one moment to say something important about
טומאה הותרה בציבור, Tuma Hutra B'Tzibur, which is תוספות Tosafot makes a
point: it is not about it being a ציבור. tzibur. יום כיפור,
Yom Kippur, the ציבור tzibur is not טמא. tamei. Okay, it is
not the fact that it's a קרבן ציבור. korban tzibur. What really
טומאה הותרה Tuma Hutra is when it is a קרבן korban that
is קבוע לו זמן, kavu'a lo zman, a fixed time קרבן. korban.
Okay, look at this little תוספות. Tosafot. טומאה הותרה בציבור. Tuma Hutra
B'Tzibur. תוספות Tosafot says, here's go אין הדבר תלוי בציבור. ein ha-davar
talui b'tzibur. This is really not- we always say טומאה הותרה בציבור,
Tuma Hutra B'Tzibur, it's really not about it being ציבור. tzibur. דתנן
בפרק הוציאו de-tenan b'perek hotzi'u שפיר פר יום הכיפורים וחביטי כהן גדול
ופסח דקרבן יחיד
הוא, she-pir par Yom HaKippurim ve-chavitei Kohen Gadol u-Pesach de-korban yachid hu,
all those things are technically private קרבנות korbanot
ודוחין שבת וטומאה, ve-dochin Shabbos ve-tuma, those do override שבת Shabbos and
טומאה. tuma. ופר העלם דבר של ציבור ושעירי עבודה זרה וחגיגה דקרבן
ציבור הם אין דוחין. U-far he-elam davar shel tzibur u-se-irei avoda zara
ve-chagiga de-korban tzibur heim ein dochin. So it's really not at all
about ציבור. tzibur. So what is it about? אלא נקיט האי כללא
בידך, Ela nakit hai klala b'yadcha, this is a great little short
תוספות. Tosafot. Let me tell you the secret. Here's what it's really
about. כל שזמנו קבוע דוחה. Kol she-zmano kavu'a docheh. If it's a
fixed time קרבן, korban, it overrides שבת Shabbos and טומאה. tuma. ואפילו
דיחיד וכל שאין זמנו קבוע אינו דוחה ואפילו דציבור. Ve-afilu de-yachid ve-chol
she-ein zmano kavu'a eino docheh ve-afilu de-tzibur. So this phrase we always
throw around טומאה הותרה בציבור, Tuma Hutra B'Tzibur, תוספות Tosafot says that's
really not what it is. It's like, you know, maybe generally true,
but it's really not about קרבן ציבור korban tzibur versus קרבן יחיד,
korban yachid, it's about a fixed time קרבן korban not a fixed
time קרבן. korban. Let's read just one more line in the גמרא
Gemara and then we'll end for today, or we might try to
get to the two dots. So the גמרא Gemara says like this.
So now we have רבי יהודה. Rebbe Yehuda. So now we have
רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* saying בדיעבד *bedieved* it doesn't work. Okay? And
that's because טומאה הותרה בציבור *Tuma's hutra betzibur*, there's no basis for
doing it based on טומאה *tuma* and בדיעבד *bedieved* it doesn't work.
So back to the גמרא *Gemara*: אי הכי רבי שמעון אומר אם
מפני הטומאה עיברוה מעוברת היינו תנא קמא *ei hachi Rabbi Shimon omer
im mipnei hatuma ibruha meuberet hainu tanna kamma*. Okay, so the תנא
קמא *tanna kamma* says nobody says you can do it לכתחילה *lechatchila*.
תנא קמא *tanna kamma* says you can do it בדיעבד *bedieved*, רבי
עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* says even בדיעבד *bedieved* it doesn't work, and רבי
שמעון *Rabbi Shimon* says בדיעבד *bedieved* it works. So רבי שמעון *Rabbi
Shimon* is the same as the תנא קמא *tanna kamma*, they're both
saying בדיעבד *bedieved* it works. אמר רבא לכתחילה איכא בינייהו *Amar Rava
lechatchila ika beinaihu*. No, the debate is לכתחילה *lechatchila*. The תנא קמא
*tanna kamma* thinks that לכתחילה *lechatchila* you can do it for טומאה
*tuma*. רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* says it doesn't work even בדיעבד *bedieved*.
And רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon* says don't do it לכתחילה *lechatchila*, but
you can, it does work בדיעבד *bedieved*. תניא נמי הכי *Tanya nami
hachi*, we taught similarly, אין מעברין את השנה מפני הטומאה לכתחילה *ein
meavrin et hashana mipnei hatuma lechatchila*. That the תנא קמא *tanna kamma*
says you don't do it לכתחילה *lechatchila*, but בדיעבד *bedieved* it works.
רבי שמעון אומר מעברין *Rabbi Shimon omer meavrin*. That you can do
it—oh, I think maybe I said it reversed. תנא קמא *tanna kamma*
says it's only בדיעבד *bedieved*. רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon* says it's even
לכתחילה *lechatchila*, מעברין *meavrin*. אלא מפני מה ביקש רחמים על עצמו *Ella
mipnei ma bikesh rachamim al atzmo*? So if you're allowed to add
a month even לכתחילה *lechatchila*, why did חזקיה *Chizkiyahu* ask for forgiveness?
שאין מעברין אלא אדר והוא עיבר ניסן בניסן *she-ein meavrin ella adar
vehu ibber nissan be-nissan*. He did it on ניסן *Nissan* itself. And
that was what his חטא *chet* was. אמר מר שאין מעברין אלא
אדר והוא עיבר ניסן בניסן *Amar mar she-ein meavrin ella adar vehu
ibber nissan be-nissan*. So let's unpack this. This claim that that was
his חטא *chet*. ולאיי ליה לחזקיה החודש הזה לכם *Velo ay leh
le-Chizkiyahu hachodesh hazeh lachem*? Now how do we know you can't do
it on ניסן *Nissan*? Based on the פסוק *pasuk*: This month is
for you. This month of ניסן *Nissan*. זה ניסן ואין אחר ניסן
*zeh nissan ve-ein acher nissan*. Only one ניסן *Nissan*, not two ניסן's
*Nissan's*. Only this month is ניסן *Nissan*. So how could he have
made that obvious mistake? So the גמרא *Gemara* says טעה בדשמואל *ta'ah
bide-Shmuel*. No, no, no. He didn't, the mistake wasn't so obvious. It's
not like on the tenth of ניסן *Nissan* he added a month.
Here was his mistake, based on what שמואל *Shmuel* says. דאמר שמואל
אין מעברין את השנה ביום שלושים של אדר *De-amar Shmuel ein meavrin
et hashana beyom shloshim shel adar*. Even if אדר *Adar*'s a 30-day
month, you can't say on אדר *Adar* the 30th day of אדר
*Adar* we're going to add an extra אדר *Adar*. Not add an
extra ניסן *Nissan*, we're going to add an extra אדר *Adar*. But
you can't say it on day 30 of אדר *Adar* because day
30 of אדר *Adar* is, could theoretically be ראש חודש ניסן *Rosh
Chodesh Nissan*. So as soon as it's possible to be ניסן *Nissan*,
you've lost the opportunity to do עיבור שנה *ibur shana*. Now that's
not so obvious. הוא ראוי לקובעו ניסן *hu ra-uy le-kov'o nissan*. והוא
סבר חוב וראוי לא אמרינן *ve-hu savar chov vera-uy lo amrinan*, that
we don't say that. So he didn't add ניסן *Nissan*. He added
a second אדר *Adar*, but he added it on day 30 of
אדר *Adar*. תניא נמי הכי *Tanya nami hachi*, we taught similarly, אין
מעברין את השנה ביום שלושים של אדר הוא ראוי לקובעו ניסן *ein
meavrin et hashana beyom shloshim shel adar hu ra-uy le-kov'o nissan*. Okay,
so what have we said? Can you add מפני הטומאה *mipnei hatuma*?
That's based on the question of טומאה הותרה בציבור או דחויה *tuma
hutra betzibur o dechuya*. If טומאה הותרה בציבור *tuma hutra betzibur*, there's
no basis of adding an extra month. And רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda*
would say טומאה הותרה *tuma hutra* and therefore even בדיעבד *bedieved* it
doesn't take effect. If you say טומאה דחויה בציבור *tuma dechuya betzibur*,
that might be okay to do it. So there's an opinion, it's
even okay לכתחילה *lechatchila*, or it's only okay בדיעבד *bedieved*. But at
least opinions that it might work either לכתחילה *lechatchila* or בדיעבד *bedieved*
to do it מפני הטומאה *mipnei hatuma*. That's one debate. The other
question is what did חזקיה *Chizkiyahu* do wrong? So although the פשט
*pshat* of the פסוקים *pesukim* is that what he did wrong was
he ate a קרבן פסח *korban pesach* בטומאה *betuma*. Okay, we're saying
no, he did something else wrong. Either what he did wrong was
he made an עיבור שנה *ibur shana* because of טומאה *tuma*, and
according to רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* you're not supposed to do that
and it doesn't work even בדיעבד *bedieved*. Or he did the עיבור
שנה *ibur shana* when it was too late, when it was אדר
*Adar* 30, and you're only supposed to do it while, before the
last day of אדר *Adar*, before אדר *Adar* 30. When we continue
tomorrow, we'll see the final opinion, which is what he did was
he had them eat, he had the טמאי *tmei* people eat the
פסח שני *pesach sheni* and he should have had them eat the
פסח ראשון *pesach rishon*. So that's the third opinion. We'll take, we'll
take a look at that when we continue tomorrow.